Guide to the Houston Comets Memorabilia Collection
University of Houston Libraries
Houston Comets Memorabilia Collection
1997-2003
2001-010
Houston Comets (Basketball team); Shuart, Carey Chenoweth
12.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection is housed in 9 boxes and organized into 5 series. The content of the collection consists of Houston Comet’s memorabilia documenting their four WNBA championship wins from years 1997 to 2000.
Historical Note:
The Houston Comets was a Women's National Basketball Association (WNBA) team based in Houston, Texas. They were formed in 1997, which was the inaugural season of the WNBA and were one of the original eight WNBA teams. The Comets were the first dynasty of the WNBA and they won more championships than any other team in the WNBA under the reigns of Head Coach Van Chancellor. They began as the sister team of the Houston Rockets under the ownership of Alexander Leslie from 1997 to 2006.
From 1997 to 2000, the Comets dominated the WNBA as they won all four championships in the first four years of the league's existence with the leadership of Cynthia Cooper, Sheryl Swoopes and Tina Thompson who were referred to as the “Big Three.” The Comets were known for courting great women's basketball stars in addition to the “Big Three” such as Kim Perrot, who succumbed to cancer in 1999 and college star Michelle Snow.
Unfortunately, the Comets failed to make another WNBA Finals appearance after their 2000 Championship season. Changes in the roster, coaching staff, ownership and playing arena prompted the demise of the Comet’s Franchise. In 2001, 2-time league MVP Cynthia Cooper retired, and in 2007, Chancellor resigned as Head Coach and Alexander sold the Franchise to Hilton Koch. Chancellor was replaced by Assistant Coach, Karleen Thompson; and shortly thereafter, the team moved from playing its home games at the Toyota Center to Reliant Arena. Given these changes over the span of seven years, the Comets struggled greatly as they only moved past the First Round of the playoffs once, which was in their 2005 season, and they failed to make the playoffs 3 out of their last eight seasons. Due to this hardship, Koch put the team up from sale in 2008, but didn’t receive any offers from investors. Consequently, the team fell under the management of the WNBA and was disbanded in the same year.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Houston Comets (Basketball team); Women's National Basketball Association
Genre/Form of Material:
Ephemera; Fliers (printed matter); Newspapers; Periodicals; Posters
Topical Term:
Basketball teams -- United States -- History
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
This collection is housed in 9 boxes and organized into 5 series. The content of the collection consists of Houston Comet’s memorabilia documenting their four WNBA championship wins from years 1997 to 2000. In addition, general Houston Comet’s novelty items can be found in this collection dating from the year 1997 to 2003.
Detailed List of Contents
- Yearbooks and Miscellaneous Items
  - Commemorative Program and Yearbooks, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Season Ticket Stubs, Booklets, and Schedules, 2000-2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Periodicals
  - Sports Illustrated for Women, May/June 2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Comets Tales, 1998, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Articles, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Houston Chronicle clippings, 1997-2000 (Ovs box 2, Ovs folder 1)
  - New York Times clippings, 1999 (Ovs box 2, Ovs folder 2)
- Printed Promotional Material
  - Flyers (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Signs (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Collector’s Card Sheets, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Collector’s Card Sheets, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Collector’s Card Sheets, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Collector's Card Sheets, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Photographic Material
  - 2000 Championship Game (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 2002 Regular Season Game (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Novelty Items
  - Posters and Banners
    - 2000 “Girl Power” team Poster (Ovs box 2, Item 3)
    - “Van’s Angels” Houston Comets Poster (Ovs box 2, Item 4)
    - “Haley,” the Houston Comet’s Mascot, Poster (Ovs box 2, Item 5)
    - WNBA 3-peat Champions Banner (Ovs box 2, Item 6)
  - Clothing and Accessories
    - Houston Comet’s T-shirt (Ovs box 3, Item 1)
    - 1997 Inaugural Season WNBA Champions T-shirt (Ovs box 3, Item 2)
    - 1997-1998 Back-to-Back WNBA Champions T-shirt (Ovs box 3, Item 3)
    - 1997-1998 Cynthia Cooper MVP T-shirt (Ovs box 3, Item 4)
    - ’97, ’98, ’99 3-peat WNBA Champions T-shirt (Ovs box 3, Item 5)
    - 1999 Western Conference Playoff T-shirt (Ovs box 3, Item 6)
    - 2000 WNBA Champions T-shirt (Ovs box 3, Item 7)
    - Cynthia Cooper Basketball Jersey (Ovs box 3, Item 8)
    - Houston Comet’s Towels and Handkerchief (Ovs box 3, Item 9)
    - Houston Comet’s Hats (Ovs box 3, Item 10)
  - Basketballs
    - #22 Sheryl Swoopes Signed Basketball (Ovs box 4, Item 1)
    - #40 Monica Lamb Signed Basketball (Ovs box 5, Item 1)
    - MVP Cynthia Cooper Signed Basketball (Ovs box 6, Item 1)
    - Plexiglas Enclosed Official Game Ball (Ovs box 7, Item 1)
  - Novelty Dolls and Toys
    - “Haley in the Box” (Ovs box 8, Item 1)
    - Nesting Dolls (Ovs box 8, Item 2)
    - Cheryl Swoopes “Celebriduck” (Ovs box 8, Item 3)
    - Miniature Cynthia Cooper Basketball (Ovs box 8, Item 4)
    - Miniature Tina Thompson Basketball (Ovs box 8, Item 5)
    - Bobble Heads: Cynthia Cooper (Ovs box 8, Item 6)
    - Bobble Heads: Tina Thompson (Ovs box 8, Item 7)
    - Bobble Heads: Sheryl Swoopes (Ovs box 8, Item 8)
    - Bobble Heads: Van Chancellor (Ovs box 8, Item 9)
  - Souvenir Water Bottles
    - Cynthia Cooper (Ovs box 8, Item 10)
    - Tina Thompson (Ovs box 8, Item 11)
    - Sheryl Swoopes (Ovs box 8, Item 12)
  - Lapel Pins and Button
    - Cynthia Cooper #14 Jersey Pin (Ovs box 8, Item 13)
    - Sheryl Swoopes #22 Jersey Pin (Ovs box 8, Item 14)
    - Kim Perrot #10 Jersey Pin (Ovs box 8, Item 15)
    - WNBA Breast Health Awareness Pin (Ovs box 8, Item 16)
    - “Fans First” Button (Ovs box 8, Item 17)
  - Miscellaneous Items
    - Heart of Champions 1999 WNBA Championship Videotape (Ovs box 8, Item 18)
    - Houston Comet's Souvenir Photo Album (Ovs box 8, Item 19)
    - Houston Comet’s Souvenir Lunchbox (Ovs box 8, Item 20)
    - Houston Comet’s Souvenir Maraca (Ovs box 8, Item 21)
    - 2000 WNBA Souvenir Championship Ring (Ovs box 8, Item 22)
    - Comets/Rockets Gift Box (Ovs box 8, Item 23)